welcome to the Femmes planers I'm
Danielle Crittenden and i'm christina
hoff sommers and we are thrilled to have
the father of all manse planers in our
studio today yes a man whisperer
and the mad genius behind the
intellectual dark web whatever welcome
to the femme Slater's Jordan Peterson
thank you very much so delighted to have
you and it's an honor to have your honor
it's um and a note to our listeners
we're recording this in front of a live
audience at the American Enterprise
Institute in Washington DC where
christina is a resident scholar and
there'll be video of the podcast as well
and we will let you know where to find
that when it's ready and we're also
grateful to AEI every week for the use
of its recording studio for the podcast
and now for an introduction though he
needs no introduction to the people here
but Jordan Peterson is a professor at
the University of Toronto and author of
many books and and poster of many
fantastic lecturers and his most recent
book has I can't keep track of how many
languages it's been translated into and
the sales just a phenomenally successful
book tour in fact my first question is
really about your tour you look pretty
good there's somebody who's visited what
a hundred cities in the past
she's January 23rd I don't know how you
do it and mostly flying well what do you
do for fun what do you ever get to relax
in brief moments and what do you do go
on Twitter and oh god yes although I
would qualify that as relaxing and I try
to you know forestall that temptation as
much as possible well I have the
automotive time that I could spend with
my wife she does travel with me and so
you know we've had we we try to take
some time to walk around the cities that
we're in and see what we can it's we're
usually not at any given place for more
than a day or two and they're usually
pretty packed up with well whatever is
associated with the lecture and then
with press that the publishers usually
arrange
I heard you interviewed in Sweden you
were in Stockholm and you were had a
half an hour to visit the city with your
wife yeah and you know you loved it but
that you know it's yeah well you tell
you take your breaks where you get them
well the thing is is that the the
lecture tour is unbelievably positive
yes and a lot of this is is ridiculously
positive you know like so if I'm going
out on the streets now or in cafes or
you know airports I meet people all the
time and they're always polite and
they're always happy to see me and they
always have some very touching story to
relate and and then the audience's
themselves are very positively
predisposed to whatever it is that we're
doing together and so that makes it a
lot easier to stay motivated and and and
to continue right you know I mean it's
demanding because everything's scheduled
so tightly and and I do a different
lecture every night every I find that
amazing because I give a lot of lectures
and I anguish over every word and then I
have another one and it I you go up
without notes yeah well I have a large
collection of you know things that I
know what how to talk about and usually
what I try to do is to formulate a
problem before the lecture so I'm
addressing a specific problem right and
then I can track how I would set up the
argument and then I walk through it but
part of it's also an attempt to
formulate the argument on the fly you
know to make the question what would you
say to formulate it more precisely and
to make a more precise and engaging
answer and then I can use the audience
to judge whether or not that's that's
happening and so it's also a real
challenge to do that so I enjoy that and
it's a excellent intellectual workout
and I've been recording the lectures and
I've been using fair some of them to
write the first draft of the chapters
for my next book and four books after
that and so you know I'm I'm able to
maximize the what would you say the
utility of doing this at each event and
and my wife seems to be particularly
well suited to
traveling like that she actually enjoys
it quite a bit and and is a very stable
person and so that's also helpful so and
you know it's nice to have an extra
brain along because things are scheduled
so tightly that we don't ever have any
room for error yes well we're going to I
can't
I don't know how intellectually rigorous
we plan to be with you today because we
know that when you ever you're on one of
these platforms you're talking about
your ideas but on the fence planners we
want to hear more a little bit more
about Jordan Peterson the man that's
desperately in definitely want to hear
about your wife Tammy yeah and also
you're so well known for your views on
men or how your ideas have been taken up
so enthusiastically by young men but we
want to talk to you about women yep
that's good so but one of the things you
and I share is that we both grew up in
Canada I promised Christine I would not
do my Canadian accent while you were
here but you grew up in rural Alberta I
grew up in Toronto and you are what the
country's most famous guru now since
Marshall McLuhan um and but is the fact
that you came from Canada have any
effect on your views do you think has it
formed you in any way I mean what did
what would it wouldn't would it be the
same if you think you'd grown up in
rural Texas how was Canada contributed
to your worldview she's always looking
for the Canadian angle well I think the
particular part of Canada I grew up in
probably was formative to some degree I
mean the town I grew up in was only
fifty years old you know and the
particular part of the world that I grew
up in was really the last settled part
of the North American Prairie this was
outside of Edmonton correct yeah both
400 miles north of Edmonton 400 miles
yeah yeah it's right at Short so it's
short yeah so the Prairie number the
Prairie stretches up that far north it
stretches up farther north in Alberta
than it does
anywhere else in the North American
continent and so we were at the tip of
viable farming essentially and so it was
it was a new place and it was a rather
raw place and it was a it was a rather
harsh place in many ways be especially
because of the winter and it was
fundamentally a working-class place
although a prosperous working-class
place right because most of the industry
there was related to the oil and gas
industry on although it was cyclical
when things were good working-class
people could make a very good living
this was during the seventies to be a
kid in 400 miles outside a small town
yeah I liked it when I was a kid I
wouldn't say it was as fun when I was a
teenager I but I'm not convinced that
you know the majority of people who are
teenagers necessarily have the most
wonderful time of it I think adults
often look backwards at the past through
rose-colored glasses I can't that's what
the cartoonist Trudeau accused Reagan of
doing continually um Gary Trudeau the
American I think the words Institute oh
no no I used for it in your book was
teenage wasteland yeah yeah but it's
Canadian as' just do you see how does
that form do you or affected you if at
all maybe it didn't it's hard to say I
mean I've lived in lots of different
parts of Canada now and and Canada is
quite different I lived in well Alberta
for a while and it had this particular
flavor of existence I mean mostly in
Fairview I was striving to leave mm-hmm
and to move ahead let's say or to move
I hesitate say up but somewhere
different somewhere more urban but
that's the case with many people I mean
the small towns all across the West in
the US and in Canada are dying
mm-hm they're they're down to nothing
because everyone's moved to the cities I
lived in Montreal for a good while and
that was interesting because it was a
very very different culture it was a
culture that was to some degree
stratified by language and by class and
none of that was true in Alberta
because it
so knew that there's no class structure
so that was quite interesting right and
you worked what I loved
pulled a passage because I think as you
say people are born in small places
everywhere and someone to leave and some
don't you said I wanted to be elsewhere
I wasn't the only one
everyone who eventually left the
Fairview I grew up knew they were
leaving by the age of twelve I knew and
my wife who grew up with me on the same
street knew well what's that thing what
would you call that what's the thing
that makes you want to leave and and set
you off because as you point out there
was no class system education was cheap
in Canada oh yeah I wasn't it wasn't
cost it was talking people you were from
a what middle class my father was a
teacher and my mother was a librarian no
no she had trained as a nurse so you
know we had a comfortable I would say
suburban lifestyle essentially you know
I'm moderate middle-class suburban
lifestyle that's what Fairview looked
like it looked like a suburb that was
built mostly in the 90s a between the
1950s in the 1970s so young Jordan and
the then young Tami and you have to tell
us that story how you met but wanted
wanted more well you know I think that's
one thing that is different to some
degree about class my father and my
mother had both left two towns they were
from and they were forward future
looking people and you know most of my
friends who quit school and who didn't
attend University they didn't have they
didn't have that sense I would say that
more developed sense of a world outside
of what they knew and the other thing is
that my my father took us on long trips
when I was a kid he was a teacher and so
he had summer holidays and we drove all
over Western Canada and down into the US
long driving trips thousands of miles
and you know that also gave us the sense
that the world was a bigger place but I
knew way before I was 12 I believed that
I was off at least to university and I
think generally in your family if you're
liable to go to university people don't
even really talk about it it's just a
given that that's what's going to happen
it's it's something that you take in
with every breath all
it's it's an uncertain and unspoken
expectation and maybe people make casual
reference like well when you go to
college but it's not like there's a
question about it
whereas if you're from a working-class
background especially if your family
hasn't pursued post-secondary education
that isn't in the realm of unspoken or
spoken expectation and it wasn't like
like lots of my friends including many
of them who dropped out before they hit
high school they weren't by they were by
no means the dimmest people in the class
like they were plenty smart but they
weren't oriented towards the idea of
pursuing a career that that involved
intellectual what intellectual
engagement wasn't in their worldview and
you know when you hear people on them
let's say more socialist end of the
distribution talk about barriers to
education they are often talk about cost
and sometimes cost is a barrier and it's
more of a barrier thing yeah and it's
more of a beer although there's still
plenty about community colleges and
state colleges where you can right get
educated for a perfectly reasonable
amount of money but for my friends no it
was never a reason that money was never
a reason they didn't pursue
post-secondary education it was more
like a truncated view of time I would
say you know there was more of an
emphasis on the here and now only and
there were jobs aplenty I guess well
there was also doubt yeah you know and
and well-paying jobs like it wasn't
obvious that you were in better shape
economically to go to university oh yeah
especially if you were doing something
like working on the oil rig right right
but Tom but you know that was rough cold
harsh work and it wasn't it wasn't once
you had an inn you could stay employed
but it wasn't that easy to land an
entry-level job either
and so yeah well it was wise for lots of
working-class people to to work in those
jobs because they were unbelievably
lucrative mm-hmm so and they should have
been because they were very difficult
and dangerous and frigid cold and and
and rough so you know it's not like the
people didn't earn their money well just
tell us quickly like how you met your
wife you were you met her when you were
and seven or eight hurt yeah great three
thank grade three yeah and you did you
fall in love with her in grade 3 grade
three yeah it wasn't mutual
[Music]
what there were lots of the boys in
grade 3 we're in love with her she had a
whole little crew of guys that were
perfectly willing to follow her around
and she was perfectly willing to exploit
that she's very good at it yeah she was
very popular it's just so wonderfully
you met his children there were friends
for a long time you know we used to play
chess together and croquet and she's a
vicious croquet player she would I don't
know if you've ever played croquet but
if it's with your balls touch then you
can stand on ears and whack it and then
the other person's ball will oh she did
vanish off into this stratosphere and
she liked to knock it all the way down
the street then she laughs so she she
always had a good sense of a good
vicious sense of humor it's one of the
things actually admire about my wife
when when we've had our verbal disputes
which you know have certainly happened
she can string together a sequence of
insults that's so hair-raising then you
have to laugh what did she have brothers
um she did she has a brother much older
eight years old because quite a peaceful
person and I rose with brothers you know
seemed to can get along with guys cuz
the they would they show love and
affection by insults yeah and jabs and
jeers and yeah and if you and I had
brother and I started learned okay I
could but if you don't have brothers
girls like oh that's so rude that's so
yeah so she was yeah well she she she
has a naturally there's maybe cuz she's
naturally twist she did well and her
father is quite sharp witted and and and
but he was a real town character he's
still alive huh he was a real character
in the town a real hyper extrovert
everybody knew him and he had a pretty
good wit on him and she had some of that
well it still had does have some of that
so she was her you know aside from her
acerbic humor and her ability to whack
balls and I
just don't want to go further on that
description that's it of many many
things that tells us about you what else
brought what else attract I mean you've
known her pretty much your whole life so
some of the other qualities that not
just attracted you but enable you to
sustain I mean I think every young
person in this room will want to know
and maybe there isn't one but what's the
secret what's it like to be with someone
that long how do you sustain that well I
think if you're fortunate some of its
some of its good fortune you know and I
would say this is true I've watched
people in their relationships
you know personally for a long time but
also as a professional because I've done
a lot of clinical counseling and I mean
there's some things that that need to be
a given about the relationship I would
say it doesn't hurt to find the other
person very attractive you know and
that's a mysterious thing we're not
exactly sure what it is that produces
let's say chemistry between people
although chemistry is definitely part of
what produces it there's subtle things
that attract people to one another that
are way below the level of consciousness
so for example women don't like the
older of men who have our each blood
factors who if they had children with
would be likely to produce a stillborn
infant well that's definitely a category
on match.com right well it's so strange
though because well that's a good
question and you know you know by older
apparently and so there's or wearing
Cologne well that then it would depend
on what type of right smell is a very
strange sense and it's very deeply tied
to very profound emotions including
memory and so you find people attractive
for reasons that you can't always
determine and so so that that was part
of it I mean I've always found her very
attractive and that continues and I I
liked her combativeness you know like I
think that there's you want someone I
think in a relationship that you can
spar with and it's partly because you
have hard problems to solve
if the person that you're with isn't
willing to put forward their opinion
then you only have half the cognitive
power that you would otherwise have you
know and hopefully you find someone
who's interestingly different from you
like not so different that you can't
communicate and you have to be careful
of that but interestingly different and
then hopefully they have the ability and
the will to express their opinion and
and then well then it's you know then
then your interest stays heightened and
there has to be that tension in a
relationship you know people think well
I I want to get along perfectly with my
partner it's like no you you probably
don't you just get bored and then you'd
go looking for trouble and so you want a
little bit of trouble in the
relationship and a little bit of mystery
and a little bit of combativeness and
and the ability to exchange opinions
forthrightly and and I trust her which
is a huge element I mean when we finally
did decide to get together permanently
we were both in our later 20s and you
know one of the things that I had
learned by that point and insisted to
her about was that we had to tell each
other the truth and she took to that
wholeheartedly you know and for better
and for worse because truths can be
harsh does that include like does this
have yeah well the truthful answer to
that is I don't answer questions that
are likely to get me in trouble yeah so
my I have a son who will answer honestly
and it's infuriating but then we
realized if you want the truth talk to
Tam well well that's the thing you know
it's it's useful to know truth is
empowering truth tellers are charismatic
and you know actually both my sons are
like brutally honest which is
disconcerting you but it's minh see that
it has made them very formidable and
because of it people trust them and the
friendships and just it gives them mood
and you've written a lot about this well
you know if I tell my wife that she
looks good in an outfit
knows that I mean it yeah and so there's
some utility in that and then if you're
silent and say I don't answer questions
that she goes and she knows well well
sometimes sometimes you know she'll say
you know do you like this and I'll tell
her that I don't and and you know and
doesn't necessarily make her happy in
the moment but but if I do say I like it
she knows that I mean it and you know
I'd actually like her sense of style a
lot so it turns out that 90% of the time
it's pretty easy for me to say look I
think you look great and mean it and you
know she's a fairly harsh standard
bearer to like she's she's insisted that
I stay in whatever reasonable physical
shape I happen to be in you know that
was that was something that she's very
demanding of and I would say that it's
the same from my side and and we've been
good at negotiating which is you know
what do you want from a partner
fundamentally what what do you want need
I mean the first thing is is that well
hopefully you like I said you're blessed
with the fact that you find each other
attractive and I think it's very
difficult for the relationship to begin
or proceed or sustain itself without
that but having that then what do you
want well you want someone that you can
trust you want someone that you can
build a view of the future with and you
want someone that you can negotiate with
and that's very hard to negotiate with
people because they have to tell you
what they think they have to know what
they want or figure it out they have to
tell you what they want they have to be
satisfied when they get what they want
which is also a very difficult thing to
manage and you have to continually
update that because your life goes
through different stages and well in
your attraction wanes as we all know it
our stage of life not fatally
necessarily for yourself but but no but
you will go I mean you will not be
twenty five forever so so that that has
to be renegotiate yeah well and you have
to work at that too right you know and
and that's something that people also
don't understand because they tend to
think that well that that all romantic
interaction should be spontaneous it's
like well if that's your theory then you
might as well just give up right now if
you're gonna
get married because that like the only
reason you can think that is because you
don't have enough responsibility to make
romantic entanglement virtually
impossible and what happens when you're
married especially when you have little
kids is that and and you both have a job
let's say is you're so busy that the
probability that you're going to find
time for spontaneous mutual interaction
is decreases to zero and so if that's
what you're hoping for then you're never
going to have it and so what you have to
do is you have to make time for each
other and you know if you're dating when
you're establishing a relationship well
you put some effort into it you know you
you decide that you're going to go out
for dinner and you dress up to some
degree and you know you try to present
yourself to each other in some halfways
mutually acceptable manner and you hope
that there's going to be a positive
consequence of that that you're going to
find each other attractive but Ben's
people somehow think that once they're
married that the same amount of effort
isn't necessary and that's wrong I would
say more effort is necessary on the same
front and you have to think it through
it's like you know if you don't want to
be bitter about the intimate element of
your relationship how much time do you
have to spend together each week and my
my rule of thumb sort of derived from
clinical observations is that you need
to spend 90 minutes a week with your
partner talking and that means you're
telling each other about your life and
staying in touch you know so that you
each know what the other is up to and
you're discussing what needs to be done
to keep the household running smoothly
and you're laying out some mutually
acceptable vision of how the next week
or the next months are going to go
together right so that that keeps your
narratives locked together like a like
the strands in a rope you need that for
90 minutes or you drift apart and you
need to spend intimate time together at
least once a week and probably more like
twice and that has to be negotiated and
if you don't negotiate it and if you
don't make it a priority then it won't
happen in all likelihood and then well
well then you don't have it and that's a
catastrophe because there's not that
many things in life that are you know
intrinsically what would you say
engaging and meaningful and pleasurable
and also bonding all of that
and if you let that go then well part of
you dies and part of the relationship
dies and well then there's always the
possibility of becoming attracted by
alternative entanglements which which
you would do if you had any spirit left
right I mean that's the thing is if well
if you're not if you're if your
relationship at home is entirely
unsatisfying sexually what are you
supposed to do with that nothing he was
supposed to just bear it I mean in one
way the answer is yes because it's your
marriage but another way is well what
that's all the fight you've got in you
you're gonna just let the erotic element
of your life die and and accept
everything that goes along with that
because you're not willing to cause a
bit of trouble to ensure that it's
maintained and you know and we're not
very good at thinking these things
through consciously and I mean people
are bad at negotiating period as far as
I can tell but they're particularly bad
at negotiating things that are deeply
private how much do you want your
partner to know about you anyways it
takes a lot of trust to have a real
conversation about what you need and
want now you have in the press people
read that you are you have a following
of young men and I went to hear your
lecture and in Washington DC and there
were a lot of women there and your book
I had first of all men don't buy books
that often compared to women so I'm
presuming you have a lot of female
readers and I found it Danielle and I
found it completely readable and for men
no it was no one it was more like a
delusional desire on the part of the
radical leftists that the only people
that could possibly be attracted to me
are angry man exam be better if they
were angry young white men you know okay
then that fits the narrative but yeah
there's a it's a you have a diverse
audience and diverse following including
many women and they're also not
particularly angry I mean are you are
diffusing the anger that's the point of
your book is stopping yes not being
resentful right well resentment is that
that's absolutely crippling right it's
resentment just zenman deceit arrogance
that's part of I'm writing
the book and one of the rules is don't
allow yourself to become resentful
resentful deceitful and arrogant things
together yeah it could be rad if you
just write well that's supposed to be
good thing so yeah I mean there's been
250,000 people as I said come to the
lectures and there hasn't been a single
negative incident this is what I find
fascinating is that I I found you early
on I said I'd had no idea you I just
that it was like Butch Cassidy and the
Sundance kids like who is that guy who
is that guy like you were pretty good
and we were covering a lot of the same
topics later on and Wow and then you
know I found out who you were
what is astonishing to me is that
there's this amazing it just split
between the positivity of your audience
the diversity of your audience the the
intellectual content of your message and
then you get with a snarky journalist
with an agenda I'm not mentioning names
but this would be this no baby no this
this young woman from GQ oh yeah and it
is beyond sight it was just like you
lady
gotcha that was Channel four we don't
want to blame the BBC it was Channel 4's
and then I and she seemed you know like
that's often she seemed intelligent and
capable of insight up to a point but
it's almost as if something had seized
her mind and she oh yes something had
something for sure I think people in
audiology can you apologize that a whole
generation some of our most talented
young women are incapable of thought
because of this idea where she thought
maybe you mean or just it's just an
openness to she couldn't and you were
saying completely like interesting
fascinating original things even to me
who've studied these topics and Wow and
no it was quite the day so I went to
Baltimore you said I did yeah well any
but it just made me think a lot that day
because I went there and I had to go out
of my way to do it not that I'm
complaining but
there's a reason for saying that you
know so I go out there and Baltimore
yeah well I was talking in both okay so
so and I showed up to the to the hotel
room where this was all occurring and
you know what you expect generally
speaking even from journalists who
aren't you know who are more of the
attack dog variety or who maybe aren't
positively predisposed to you
ideologically or personally you expect a
certain modicum of professional
politeness right you know because well
you don't have to be there and you came
and you in vyx eped it an invitation and
all of that and so even with the channel
4 journalist Kathy Newman
she was quite polite and and forthcoming
in the in the green room before the
interview you know it so she would have
at least that professional persona which
is it's not nothing right there there's
something to be said for for going
through the emotions professionally in
an appropriate manner but when I walked
into the hotel room in Baltimore it was
obvious that this interviewer had
already made up her mind about me a
hundred percent and that she was
absolutely you know negatively
predisposed to me with a personal animus
an animus is exactly the right word and
there was about a half an hour
photography session because it was GQ
and so I was in that atmosphere the
photographers were fine I was in that
atmosphere for about 45 minutes before
we started to talk and part of the
reason that I'm so I'm not as calm
during that interview as I usually am
I'm a little bit harsher and the reason
for that is that you know it just
started off instantly combat it and and
what I what I should have done you see
it's very very difficult to be awake
enough to do these things properly and
and the interview progressed fine
although by the end of it I thought that
I had maybe done enough interviews for a
while because I didn't think I had
regulated my temper as well during that
interview as I might have well for the
first two minutes you were getting and
then she brought up a question about
anger and I just saw you kind of adjust
and then after that it was smooth
well that's good because it was
touch-and-go you know and I thought boy
you know maybe you're running out of
patience maybe you you know maybe it's
time to dial back on the interviews
because you know I've had many
interviews like that and they're very I
find them like and it takes me like
three days to recover I know and then
you got you start thinking yourself like
what I should have said I should have
said that and I Drive myself mad no but
you did very well but it's so
interesting that what it told me was how
parochial she was and she lives in her
own little world isn't it more a little
bit about the ideology of our time and
gosh you encountered this everywhere and
I used to write about this wisely I put
I would encounter it I mean I think part
of the issue is that you will
acknowledge that there are differences
between the sexes that seems to be I
know that's a hell of a heresy that's a
heresy because when I was reading your
book there is nothing about it that is
anti female in fact you you do a lot of
examination of the Adam and Eve story
and you have this wonderful passage
about like Adam being the originally
aggrieved man who throws a woman under
the perfect God you do you made her and
the rules such as they are you know they
seem very commonsensical they could
apply to anyone so is that a fair
surmise of why you get so attacked that
just the very fact that you're willing
to speak about the sexes as being not
unequal but different but equal yeah
well you know what I would say that
that's part of it because there's a
threat there so one of the things that
happened when I was in Scandinavia I
just wrote a call him about this
actually it was interesting being in
Scandinavia especially in Sweden because
they pushed the equality of opportunity
doctrine farther than any other country
they invented it it almost started there
and there like in the UN and the
original
the Charter the Swedes were there
they've never given no no and so and the
week that I was there was the same week
that two articles were published on
gender differences in in temperament and
in interest and the biggest sex
differences that we know of that aren't
morphological are in interest so women
are more interested in people by and
large and men are more interested in
things by and large and the difference
is actually large it's one standard
deviation and so that means if you're a
man you would have to be more interested
in people than 85% of men to be as
interested as 50% of women and if you're
a woman you'd have to be more interested
in things than 85% of women to be as
interested as the 50th percentile male
so the difference is actually quite
substantial and it's certainly large
enough to drive occupational choice
differences and it explains a lot about
the configuration of people in the work
absolutely well and you know we're
approaching parity in terms of workplace
overall workplace distribution women but
there's massive difference as an
occupational choice like it's very
interesting for example to go to the
website of the US Labor Department and
look at male and female dominated
industries and you know there's the the
top 10 male-dominated industries have
basically zero women in them people
bricklayers being wonderful like people
there are people through zones
according to Camille Palio you find just
a lot of men in the people free zone
yeah yeah yeah and the women are in you
ask a group of women and men would you
rather spend the next three weeks taking
a part of machine and putting it
together or helping a group of people
work out their problems and the pool of
people who want to do the machine it's
just far more men than well and there's
more men in women dominated industries
than there are women and men dominated
industries at the extreme so that's like
nurse nursing yeah yes it is way more
male nurses and more bricklayers
I've studied these male nurses and they
already you know gender activists are
upset because
they earn more than women and a
professor of Nursing at the University
of Pennsylvania tried to find out why
and she found out they immediately find
out what's the best paying field
subfield so they go into like nurse
anesthesiology it pays a lot more the
men are there and just proportionate
number and they're willing to work in
CREP you know in st. hours they're far
more willing to with gender differences
is that men are more willing to move
longer hours yeah they're more willing
to to work outside they're more willing
to take on dangerous tasks they're more
likely to work in scalable industries so
like you can't scale personal care it's
really very it's very very difficult
they're much less likely to work
part-time if they have small businesses
they're much more likely to work
full-time in the small business rather
than this then part-time yeah and I mean
women have their reasons to want to work
part-time and Farrell also pointed out
that if you work 10% longer hours you
make 40% more money nonlinear nonlinear
return on overtime that's something
that's really useful to know you know
it's closer to an employer they have
some but it also marks you out you know
like if you have 10 employees and
they're all doing the reasonable job
let's say but one of them is working in
extra half an hour a day or 45 minutes a
day and you can observe that every day
then that gives them an edge with
regards to potential promotion and so
and the return on those edges is
nonlinear and so anyways so I went to
Scandinavia and it was the same week
that two studies were released showing
what had already been established beyond
a shadow of a doubt that the personality
differences between men and women and
the differences in interest as well
actually get bigger as your society gets
richer and as it gets more egalitarian
and and not just a little bit either
that's the other thing that's so
interesting is you might think well the
effect is it's the opposite of what the
social constructionist would predict
first of all so that's the first thing
to point out is it's not only that their
hypothesis wasn't supported it was
decidedly refuted and and none of them
have come to terms with that and and and
it's not a small effect the the the
difference between personality between
men and women in Scandinavia is a lot
larger than
ideas in 90 Gillett area contract in
rural Botswana that's also true in the
United States the richer the Democratic
your household demographic your
household the more likely the woman is
to take town time out and be at home
with right you can afford it you can
afford to do it and she can afford to
major in what odd you know low-paying
fields like I don't know a feminist
dance therapy the other thing you see
one of the things that's also
interesting I think is that you know
there's this idea that mate
that marriage is a patriarchal
institution you know that's primarily
put there for the for the utility of the
of the male and think well like I think
that's complete bloody rubbish and I
don't think there's any evidence to
support it at all but I think the best
counter evidence is that well if that's
the case then rich people shouldn't be
getting married because they don't have
to oppress themselves but the truth of
the matter is is that the higher your
demographic position the more likely you
are to be married so marriage is falling
apart among you know in the more likely
the wife is staying home and but not I
mean she will has all sorts of pursuits
but she's not well there's an old saying
anyone any woman who marries for money
earns it yes but now okay this is where
you might get in a little trouble
because in your book you call men order
and women chaos and you say order the
known appears symbolically associated
with masculinity and chaos the eternal
feminine is also the crushing force of
sexual select yeah what's up with that
yeah chaotic okay well it isn't
men and women that are ordering chaos
it's masculinity and femininity
symbolically and so what's happened
fundamentally is that where our brains
are wired for social cognition so we're
not natural scientists or natural
sociologists that might be of bidders
even though I shudder to think that that
might be true especially yes well that's
yes okay triggering or maybe yeah or
ma'am or maybe were more were more
naturally people who observe through the
lens of fiction and that what we see is
the world as characterized and the world
obviously is made out
men and women and children and those
seem to be our fundamental cognitive
categories masculinity femininity and
and and and then the category of
children and those categories have
expanded to take on connotations outside
of pure person perception and so you
know it's for this reason that if you go
to a movie and maybe it's a Disney
animated movie and I like to talk about
those because they draw on a very deep
symbolic well it's perfectly reasonable
to see a witch that lives in a swamp
because those go together like it makes
sense you know the witch doesn't live in
a gleaming chrome high-rise you know she
lives in a swamp guess that's in maybe a
quarter room I think well that's it
that's well the hybrids would be better
for that right you can take off better
but there are categories of symbolic
Association that are natural to the way
we think and the fundamental elements of
those categories seem to be gendered and
so this is partly why I make reference
to Taoism for example so for the Daoists
the world is made out of chaos and order
and chaos is the domain that you don't
understand and that emerges
unpredictably but also the domain from
which new forms emerge right because
it's from novelty that the new emerges
and i think the fundamental association
between femininity is chaos is the
association between what's unexpected
and novel and what's new because new
forms emerge from chaos and it's not
that chaos is is bad an order is good
that that's no book both have their
pathology both have their virtue
yes yes and and and what you're looking
for and this is this is what the book
concentrates on above all is that you're
looking constantly to find the balance
between those two so for example
formally speaking the domain of order is
that place that you are when what you're
doing is producing the results that you
want to have produced so imagine imagine
think about the preconditions for not
being anxious okay so the preconditions
are that you're constantly making
predictions about what's going to happen
next
and those predictions are tied tightly
to your behavioral output so you act in
a certain way and you presume that a
certain thing is going to happen and if
your actions produce the results that
you desire then you assume that you know
where you are and you know what you're
doing and that your plan is intact and
that the environment is secure and that
keeps your anxiety under control that's
order and then you know maybe you're at
a party and you don't know anybody and
you tell a joke and everybody looks at
you like what you said was not only not
funny but also downright offensive and
then all of a sudden you've moved from
the domain of order into the domain of
chaos because you thought you were
somewhere and you thought you were
someone and you were thought you were
with people that were of a certain type
and you got all that wrong and so if you
also suggesting it is gonna be the woman
who says I find that really open but
women are also more sensitive to
negative emotion so there is some
slightly higher probability that that
might be the case but then I think women
are also associated at least in men's
imaginations with nature which is part
of the chaotic domain say as opposed to
culture because they're sexually
selective so you've got to think what is
nature I mean we have that as a
cognitive category right we think of the
natural world we think of nature versus
culture it's a fundamental opposition
what is nature well nature is trees and
landscapes and animals and all of that
but that isn't what nature fundamentally
is nature fundamentally is that which
selects from a genetic perspective
that's nature that's the fundamental
definition of nature and it is the case
that human females are sexually
selective and it's it's a major
component of human behavior so the the
evolutionary theory roughly speaking is
that the reason we diverged from
chimpanzees eight million years ago 7
million years ago is at least in part
because of the differences between
sexual selectivity between female humans
and female chimpanzees female
chimpanzees are more likely to have
offspring from
and males but it's not because of their
sexual selectivity so a female
chimpanzee has periods of fertility that
are marked by physical by observable
physiological changes not the case with
human females human female ovulation is
is concealed so that's a very profound
biological difference between human
females and chimpanzees and the
chimpanzee females will mate with any
male but the dominant males chase the
subordinate males away but human females
are sexually selective and so and it's
not a trivial fact so you have twice as
many female ancestors as male ancestors
you think well how can that be well
imagine that on average every single
human female has had one child
throughout the entire course of history
which is approximately correct
by the way then imagine that half of the
man had zero and the other half had two
okay and that's roughly the case so half
of males historically speaking have been
repres and the reason for that is
because of female sexual selectivity so
it is actually the case that female
humans are nature it's not only that
they're that that they're associated
with nature symbolically as far as repre
is concerned they are the force of
nature that does the selection and so
their nature in the most fundamental way
and there is a chaotic element of that
at least in relationship to men and also
in relationship to women because a lot
of the female on female competition is
competition that's chaotic for the right
to be sexually selective right not only
with regards to men which drives a lot
of politicking but also in relationship
to each other because part of what human
females do is jockey for position in the
female dominance hierarchy for the top
position which is the woman who gets to
be most sexually selective and so that
draws female female competition and it's
a different dynamic there's there's
similarities between female female
competition and male-male competition
but there are also differences and
they're pronounced so men for example
while men are more likely to compute
compete for socioeconomic status and
that's partly because that drives female
made choice so the correlation for men
between
socioeconomic status and sexual success
is about 0.6 and for women it's 0-0 in
fact it's actually slightly negative so
and that's a huge difference between men
and women but you know that you know the
anthropologist Sarah hurdie Hrdy
and she's like my favorite feminist
theorist although as she would say I'm a
theorist who happens to be a feminist
but she studied primate behavior and she
watched she looked at the women very
care they were the females and I went
very carefully and looked at it
chimpanzees and gazelles and found that
the female minissha like male
primatologists would look and say oh the
females the males are dominant and the
females are so cooperative she looked
more carefully and so the females
weren't exactly cooperative like they
would pass around their infants their
baby
you know whenever they were and would
fine and so the male primatologist say
oh they're they're so kind and caring
she found out that when it was not your
it was not hers they would take little
Tufts of hair that wouldn't come out or
they'd do something to the eyes and and
the baby would like be injured and she
saw all this violence especially true in
their status differentiation yes so
that's much more likely that'll happen
when a higher status female is taking
care of a lower status infant exactly
and she said the great tragedy well not
tragedy she'd the reality of our species
in fact the subtitle of her book is that
the woman who never revolved we didn't
evolve for niceness and cooperative
there's an immense competition and we
can according to her we are its
indelibly you know marked in our nature
to compete for the dominant males and
there's in - and that seems to cross
culturally as well that does flatten out
a little bit in the more egalitarian
societies yeah instead of being
exaggerated it does flatten to some
degree so you could imagine that there's
a biological component and a cultural
component and both in in in that case if
you modify the cultural component then
that seems to
decrease the overall so like let me be
more clear about this
women are less prone to mate up across
an up status hierarchies in Scandinavia
than they are in less egalitarian
countries but they're still prone to do
it so worldwide for example women young
women find men who are about four years
older than them maximally attractive and
they tend to mate across and up status
hierarchies and so one of the
consequences of that for example is that
as women have entered the workforce
they've actually driven inequality
because rich women will only marry rich
men men as rich as them or richer
whereas rich men will marry women who
are poorer than them but women won't and
so what that means is it's another
factor that's pooling wealth in the
hands of fewer and fewer people this is
also sorted of mating now and you just
find someone with your background you
wear as a doctor might have once married
is secretary you now marries another
doctor yeah well can I ask then stepping
a little bit back from primates as well
how does this selection work in the era
of swiping right and left how what is
your reaction to the way young people
date today oh that's a good I was really
hoping we'd get into that you were very
into the monkeys so I didn't want to
interrupt no no well well I should close
off the Scandinavian discussion just by
pointing out and this is something that
the Scandinavians are really going to
have to wrestle with is that if you
Institute effective policies to promote
equality of opportunity which the
Scandinavians have done you're going to
produce some equality so like a 50-50
distribution of men and women in the
workplace but you're also going to
exacerbate certain kinds of inequality
and you can't get it out of that so you
cannot have equality of opportunity and
equality of outcome together they don't
work together an equality of outcome the
essential equality of outcome doctrine
which is often described with the code
word equity is that at every level of
every occupation the people have to be
represented by the same number that
they're represented in at the population
so if it's not 5050 men and women at
each in each occupation any and in each
Strada at each occupation then that sort
of prima facie evidence for
discrimination and for systemic
discrimination it's like nope sorry you
have to factor in choice and choice
actually turns out to be a very
important determinant and as this
society gets flatter and flatter choice
becomes a more important a more and more
important determinant and so you so what
that essentially means is that the most
radical end of the left-wing political
agenda is logically impossible in fact
it's impossible for a variety of other
reasons and they should look at the data
I mean it it's just a cliche now of in a
group of activists and they'll say oh
well we need in order for women to
achieve equality we need government
funded day care and we need they have it
in Sweden yeah Sweden has fewer women in
managerial levels American women are
ahead in fact now they have Jenna they
have quotas over there so they need
female CEOs and females on board hasn't
made any difference
they're bringing in mime American women
because we're so much further ahead so
it's like no difference in the
distribution of men and women lower than
though it's it's called the Nordic
paradox and okay you guys are so wonky I
will get back okay yeah yes that's good
good well we all want to get back to
well I was thinking this morning about I
was talking to a variety of political
types and we were talking about this
morning yeah in DC it hard to believe
hard to believe no I'm not I'm not
telling you a bunch of Republicans here
and I've been talking to Democrats as
well but it was mostly Republicans here
and we were talking about abortion and I
made a case that that's really not a
very productive discussion because
you're talking about a problem way too
late in the sequence of problems so by
the time the discussion starts to be
about abortion there's 50 problems that
have already emerged that no one has
addressed and some of those problems are
the fundamental problem is how human
beings should regulate their sexual
behavior and that's a big problem and
you think well and there's an
interesting thing that's happening
you know the people on the right would
say well that's easy is like don't sleep
around and and get married and have sex
with your marital partner and that's all
the problem
so there's strictures on sexual behavior
and those would be the traditional ones
and what you see on the left is that
there's this weird paradoxical demand
let's say that people should be allowed
to express their sexuality in any manner
that they choose whenever they want but
that sex is so dangerous that it has to
be carefully regulated at every single
stage of the interaction and so you know
that many state legislatures have now
followed the example of university
campuses and put it in affirmative
consent legislation so that every move
you make towards physical intimacy has
to be preceded by the instantiation of a
verbal contract essentially it's like
well can I take your hand yes you
actually from what I understand you
actually have to say yes
like nodding is not sufficient and so
and so each stage has to be it has to be
preceded by affirmative consent and you
know which which well I won't I won't
say anything about yeah I will it's
absurd it's absurd to assume that that's
how human intimate relationships are
supposed to proceed and then you have
complicated laws emerging that are part
of that that for example this is the
case in California as I understand it is
that you cannot give affirmative consent
if you're intoxicated okay so you think
about that it's like well what does that
mean it means that like a lot of sex
Jesus has been illegal for a long time
including marital marital yes it's nice
to me on my honeymoon okay
well buddy I'm rethinking it it seems it
seems to me it seems to me
it seems to me to mean the California
legislation that if you have sex with
your wife or husband and either of you
is intoxicated then you're either one of
you or both is guilty of rape that's
what it looks like to me actually I was
in a debate a few years ago at the
University of Virginia law school and I
turned to my debate partner and said so
if what you're saying is right two
people can rape one another hmm right
she said yes and I said oh I mean how
can that be well that that's the
question well okay so then I would say
well it's interesting because I think
that a lot of this confusion has emerged
fundamentally as a consequence of the
birth control pill so you know cuz you
got to think situationally before you
think ideologically or psychologically
it's like it seems to me that the 20th
century will be remembered for the
hydrogen bomb the transistor and the
birth control pill and those are
unbelievably radical technological
innovations and maybe the most yeah but
my fairly on the door it's dependent on
the transistor you know cuz I spawned
all of that so that that's the big
technological innovation that spawned
all that and of the three I would say
the the birth control pill is probably
the bigger hydrogen bomb so and because
it it changed the fundamental biological
nature of women and men and because it
gave women for the first time in
biological history the the option of
choosing their reproductive status yeah
and that's that's we like that that's
absol yes and no like yes we like it but
it's not something that's come without a
tremendous its complexity a fellow can
have you been reading no no I think
you'll find him interesting is easy
right well I'm not I'm not making a case
for the abolition of the birth control
pill by any stretch of the imagination
but I'm pointing at its complexity and
so because one of the questions is well
once you can regulate your reproductive
function what attitude should you have
towards sex
and one answer might be the more of it
under the more varied circumstances the
better because why not and I would say
that was actually part of the attitude
that emerged in the aftermath of the
birth control pill in the 1960s right
and it was it was a reasonable response
in some sense because it's such a
cataclysmic change that you don't know
what it implies well what's the
consequence of that well first of all
people aren't reliable enough to use
birth control in an entirely reliable
manner so even though it can work at
near 100% efficiency you have to take it
extraordinarily regularly and in a
disciplined manner for that to work and
so there was still the problem of
unwanted pregnancy let's say and then
there was the problem of the
proliferation of sexual epidemics and
that culminated in AIDS which you know
could have easily wiped all of us out
but didn't but there are other sexual
epidemics that could have had the same
effect but we've been fortunate enough
to escape them and and then and then
more recently there's been this weird
inversion especially on the radical left
that points to the re-emergence of
something like a set of sexual taboos
you know like I think the idea that sex
is casual and that it's a form of
entertainment is I think it's an
absolutely preposterous idea I think
that it's it's psychologically shallow
beyond belief to hold that as a core
proposition because it forces you to
first of all if it's repetitive sex with
multiple partners it it forces you to
treat people as if they're
interchangeable and I don't see how
that's good for you psychologically or
for the people that you're using
interchangeably it it implies that you
can divorce sexuality from play from the
desire for a relationship from emotional
fragility from love from family from
responsibility all of those things that
are part
of everyone and I don't think you can
and I don't think people's experience
indicates that you can and especially on
the emotional front and I think that's
partly what's driving and there's also a
residual sense that there's something
about sex that's fundamentally dangerous
and maybe it's dangerous emotionally and
personally and maybe it's dangerous
socially and psychologically which it
most certainly is because it's a
powerful force and the way the left is
reacting to that is by insisting that
all forms of sexual behavior are valid
and and and that it's reasonable to
manifest all of them but that it's
simultaneously so dangerous that
absolutely every aspect of it has to be
state regulated and in an increasingly
draconian form and so I think what needs
to happen is that the left and the right
have to get together and have a like a
real discussion about what constitutes
fell in sexual morality and that's the
conversation you have to have way before
you worry about solving like the
abortion debate which you know is very
divisive and very and very intractable
one of the things we talked about
actually just last week on the podcast
is this cover story in the Atlantic
about the sexual recession among young
people that despite the advent of the
birth control pill abortion is is going
down it's that there's a there's Lexus
and I think is going down hook up fewer
arms have you can't help into that
you're about in on that well if you
raise the cost of something you decrease
its prevalence you know and and I think
that it's it seems to be you know a
Juris now don't know why I kind of think
that it's also a reflection of the same
thing that bloomberg reported on just a
few days ago they said that across
businesses men are thinking I'm not
spending any time with a single woman
that isn't you know associated with me
in some formal manner like my wife I'm
not going to do it I'm not going to
mentor young women I'm not going to be
in a room alone with them because I
could face career annihilation
absolutely and instantly they they're
frightened of young women escape Julian
said that's part of it but we can over
exaggerate the part I mean anxiety and
depression is going up amongst both
young men and young women suicide is
going up that that there's it's not just
a
you know most people I think are not
we're talking about an elite demographic
who is into the consent and political
correctness and work with their this is
across the board and its global it's in
it's happening even in Sweden it's
really happening in Japan yeah and Japan
exactly so so many things are and that
speaks to and especially in Japan they
have people especially young men have
given up on intimacy and that having sex
is actually I mean that had too much
trouble
sex robots right well right well and
there's pornography
yeah there's photography basically zero
risk meters when you allow for
pornography that that that men and women
will sort of separate that from their
actual sex anyway we're seeing a whole
I guess collapse of intimacy let alone
sex and and and and and I don't think
that's just explained by the political
nature so I I'd be interested in your
thoughts yeah well I don't know that I
don't know the literature on the decline
in sexual activity well enough to know
if it's valid or reliable mhm but I mean
I mean I think that you know in a stable
society you take lots of things for
granted you take you take the fact that
men and women are going to be sexually
attracted to one another for granted and
even though it's more fragile than it
appears you know it and it's suppressed
more easily than you might think and you
take the idea that men and women are
going to move together towards the
establishment of long-term intimate
relationships for granted but that's
partly because you don't understand what
invisible preconditions exist to make
that self-evident you know and when
those invisible preconditions are
disrupted by rapid technological or
sociological change then things shift
underneath you and you don't know why
like a lot of it is traced to the advent
of the smartphone especially in the
Generation Z that that a Kate was
explaining this to us that you could see
it was broadband internet and the
smartphone that led to this you know
increasing fall-off of relationships
yeah well maybe the abstract is more
interesting than right
you see that good I just wanted I want
to know the truth have you ever been
with somebody you loved and I'm
fascinating all that but you really want
to get back to your smartphone has that
ever happened yeah well it happens all
the time
it happens to me no it happens during
our podcast and I'm kind I'm researched
well they're very or they're very
addictive they're very addictive you
know I read the other day that but
they're very alluring they are kind of
going together the preferred method of
interpersonal communication between
young people now is testing rather than
face-to-face communication right and the
swiping the Apes
yeah well that's that's a whole that's
that's a very interesting topic too that
the like the tinder phenomenon that's
because that that's an also a major
technological revolution because what
it's done I would say for the first time
is reduce the cost of rejection to males
to zero because it hides it the only
people you ever hear from our people who
haven't rejected you although although
they true but but there was one man who
had to make 300 he key actually tallied
it yeah he had to make 300 requests of
swiping right yeah
to one replies already he had the sense
of sure sure sure but it's massively
attenuated because you're not being
humiliated not at all not at all it's
really it's really at arm's length and
you know you can swipe very very rapidly
and so you can get all that rejection
over within a very short period or less
be worse not I mean not nearly as bad
yeah so and you know I I don't know what
and I mean tinder also reduces the one
of the other things that things that you
want to think about with regards to sex
and I think this is probably
particularly true for women is that to
what degree is it in women's interests
to allow the cost of sex to fall to zero
because with pornography certainly does
that and it just seems to me that that's
not a very good long-term strategy for
relationships between men and women
because whatever sex is worth the cost
of zero is the wrong price and so that's
you know I bunnyranch and paid quite a
bit for
well true true but you but that's true
but you know you don't have to and you
know I've heard from a number of women
what written read blog reports on their
frustration with their attempts to be
relatively sexually selective like let's
say they decide that they're not going
to sleep with their new partner on the
first date you know they're frustrated
by the fact that to the degree that
they're being cautious in their sexual
behavior which i think is actually an
admirable idea that they're instantly
out competed especially if their
partners are somewhat impulsive by women
who will say yes at the drop of a hat
and so well again I don't think you know
it depends on what the goal is that's
the thing is that there's the short
terms their short-term sexual
gratification but the literature
indicates that married couples for
example or couples in a permanent
long-term monogamous relationship are
more sexually satisfied than single
people and maybe the single people have
to be parsed out into those who are
sexually successful and those who aren't
but I suspect that wouldn't make that
much difference but whatever there's the
utility of relatively immediate sexual
gratification for whatever that's worth
and the adventurousness that goes along
with that let's say the hunt and the
excitement of having a new partner and
all of that and maybe even the danger
that's associated with that because
people like to have a little bit of
danger in their life but what's the goal
it's like what do people want and I mean
there's a great book called a billion
wicked thoughts that was written by
Google engineers and so it contains
great psychology because Google
engineers don't care about political
correctness and they just write down
what they find and they don't even
notice that it's politically incorrect
hence James tomb or for example and what
they found was that women use
pornography just as much as men but the
pornography that women use is verbal
it's not imagistic and that the
pornographic novels essentially follow
the same extraordinarily standard
plotline to the degree that publishing
houses like Harlequin which I was going
to say it's the it's the bodice rippers
that's right snob yeah right so in the
Harlequin series you have you know the
that were published like in the 1970s
that are pretty they're tame well
there's a variety they range from they
range from mpletely tame to essentially
to hardcore pornography but the but the
plots are quite similar and the plot is
you know young relatively innocent woman
finds powerful interesting dangerous
male tames him and then they live happy
yeah it's the beauty in the beasts plot
search for women on pornhub we
discovered we did an episode on porn was
for women it was getting rape wasn't
that like there's no lesbianism or at
least that was your port yeah that was
yours on me okay my port is going to the
williams-sonoma store I know it is it is
female all those men and women should
never tell one another their fantasies
because when they're outraged by what we
say and we're totally bored by what they
say and I thought like women have kind
of these scenarios and you know I don't
know you know I don't know what their
storylines storylines and matters like I
don't want to say this to you but if
there's a lot of just close-ups of
female body parts yeah well men are much
more visually oriented I know sexually
and but now they're being shamed I mean
now that it's called the male gaze mm-hm
and so there's all of us think oh my god
the Sports Illustrated is exploiting the
female forget it yeah baby men like it
and I'm worried that now sort of the way
in the past sexual sub you know gays
were shamed we're now reversing it and
shaming like heterosexual
yes--that's differ we had the young
woman who complained about being
whistled at and I said don't worry it
stops yeah do we have a little bit of
time for a couple more topics with you
because one of the things that is coming
out of this younger generation and you
have a chapter of it in your book which
I'm sorry I wanted to finish what the
line that we were pursuing I do this
well with sexual behavior the question
is what's the endgame and then this is
what people have to ask themselves is
like one of the coral
to the female pornographic romance is
actually the establishment of a
long-term relationship and the question
is you know it's so funny because I got
pilloried in the New York Times for
talking about enforced monogamy
squirty because that gets brought up
like in everyone I talked to that woman
for two days I know it's just like a
little side comment and then that became
like a showcase like like in forced
monogamy you mean forced marriage no I
mean that was an anthropological term
what she knew perfectly well because
she's a very smart person and all it
means is that there's a pronounced
proclivity in human societies around the
world to enforce monogamous
relationships at multiple levels of the
sociological hierarchy you do it
culturally you do it you do it in
expectation you do it legally you know
an enforced monogamy so if my son was
just married and if he came to me next
year and he said you know okay dad guess
what I've managed to have four Affairs
in the last year with heart women and my
wife hasn't found out about any of them
I'm not going to pat him on the back and
say good job kid you know I'm gonna say
what the hell's up with you you know you
violated the vow that you took you're
putting your whole future risk you're
betraying yourself and your wife and
well that's enforced monogamy you know
the the idea is that the social norm is
the establishment of a long-term
monogamous relationship and that there
are strictures put in place to support
that but also to punish deviation from
it and you say well you know maybe maybe
not so much on the punishment in but you
can it depends it's like what do you
want what what is it that you want you
want a long-term stable relationship or
not and if that's the goal then your
behavior should be devoted to whatever
it is that facilitates that goal and I
don't see that I certainly don't see
that casual and impulsive sex fits that
bill now not in the least and all of the
evidence with regards to living together
shows that that's actually detrimental
to the establishment of a long-term
relationship so first of all common-law
marriage people who are in common-law
marriage are much more likely to be
divorced so that's the first thing the
second thing is people who live together
before they get married are much more
likely to be divorced after they get
married
the idea that well you can try someone
on for size and see how it works and
then you're gonna see if you're
compatible it's like that's one story
another story is how about you and I
live together for a little while and you
know if you're you're not so bad but
maybe I can find someone better and if I
do you know in the next year and a half
or so because we're not hooked together
in any formal way I can just trade you
in it's okay you can do the same to me
but I don't really see that as the sort
of complimentary mutual interaction that
leads to the formulation of long term
trust and I think it's a better story
for interpreting what constitutes living
together then well you know we're gonna
try each other out because that's what
mature people would do rental yeah well
that's right wash the rental yeah yeah
well that's that's it and and and but
what more most importantly the data
indicate that it doesn't work is that
you're more likely to get divorced not
less likely because maybe the right
attitude is well you're probably about
as flawed as me and you know we're lucky
that we found each other and so let's
see if we can make a commitment because
we're engaging in something that's very
risky you know an intimate relationship
and we're gonna commit to each other and
see if we can build something of value
across time and there's a definite of
risk in that but there's a complement to
your partner it's like well I think
you're worth making a sacrifice for and
what's the sacrifice well it's everyone
else it's a big sacrifice and there's
and if you don't see that as a
compliment then I don't think you're
thinking because not only is it a
compliment it's sort of like the
ultimate compliment and maybe you don't
get to have a marriage that works
without that compliment maybe it's so
difficult to establish a long-term
relationship that's functional that you
have to make a walloping sacrifice very
early on in the relationship in order
for that to even be a possibility and
you know maybe not because what the hell
do we know about what binds people
together but but it's not that easy to
stay with someone for a long period of
time you know it's it's a real it's a
real commitment it takes a tremendous
amount of effort so yes it that actually
you're bringing us back to the beginning
and your time with Tammy and one of the
things about I think I'm gonna guess
this is a bit of an overlooked part in
your chapter in your book but I just was
like one of my favorites it
was your book on modern parenting oh yes
and that was the one I thought I would
get most trouble for I know but critics
don't read that far into the book well
well it my mother when I had my first
child gave me a 1950s copy of dr. Spock
and he was considered so controversial
and yet he was just like the most
sensible person made new children very
very well was a pediatrician and you
your rule for parenting is do not let
your children do anything that makes you
dislike them and you kind of in that one
chapter and it's not even one of your
longest chapters just did this wonderful
sweeping overview of modern parenting
and the problems and in some ways that
we're producing maybe some of these kids
who are prolonging adulthood prolonging
the markers of adulthood that that you
feel that parents you said you see
today's parents is terrified by their
children not least because they've
denied credit for their role as
benevolent and necessary agents of
discipline order and conventionality and
then you told some hilarious stories
about when your wife ran a daycare
center out of your house and you would
you would get into tests of wills with
some of the two-year-olds but son is
ordinary or deep here he got married he
still doesn't want to do anything he
doesn't want to do yeah he's very
charming yeah and very emotionally
stable so it's like he's easy to get
along with but trying to get him to do
something he doesn't want to do it's
alright
he had my wife defeated when he was nine
months old and she's tough like it
seriously she's no pushover but he would
just sit there with his mouth closed and
glare at hers like I'm not eating that
and I can take more than you can dish
out it was really something to see you
know to see that kind of force of will
in someone not small talk a little bit
about that and just the modern roles
between men and women I mean we're less
you know they're you don't really you're
not really supposed to distinguish
between fathers and mothers even though
that seems to inevitably happen in most
well it happens in large part because
the children differentiate between them
like parents are under the delusion that
most of what you do with your children
is driven by what you want to do with
your children when in fact it's driven
to a massive due
by what your children want you to do
with them and so there were studies done
thirty years ago on feminist parents who
decided that they were going to raise
their children in non gender
differentiated manners and when they
were studied they found that the parents
who had that explicit philosophy were
just as gender differentiated with their
children as the parents who didn't have
the philosophy and the reason for that
is that if you're a parent that has any
sense at all you don't respond to your
children as a rigid ideologue you
respond to them as whatever it is the
child man manifests it him or herself as
like you know with any individualized
relationship you take your cue from the
person and you might think while a child
has no intrinsic nature but you know if
you think that you either don't have
children or you've never seen a child or
you're so blinded by your Radiology that
you don't have a child you just have a
blank projection screen onto which you
project your presuppositions and then
heaven help your child you know so so a
lot of the gender differentiation is
actually driven by the children's
demands and and that's all for the good
that chapter I thought I would get into
tremendous trouble for writing that
chapter because it's contentious right
on the surface this the rule because the
rule first implies that children can be
dislikable and then I would say again
you know it's like have you met children
exactly a child where they're children
you didn't like obviously and it's a
lots of children are dislikeable but
it's taboo to admit that because they're
all sweetness and light and innocence
ever since Rousseau but you know who so
put all five of his children in an
orphanage where they all died so maybe
we won't know so we won't talk too much
about Rousseau and and then the next
taboo is well that parents can dislike
their children but if you're a clinician
and you don't think that parents can
dislike their children then well then
well then you're not a clinician because
one of the things you constantly see is
that pathology within families is an
incredibly common source of
psychological destabilization right and
it's terrible tension between parents
and their children and between siblings
what I suggest in the in the book which
I think is radical by today's standards
is that your fundamental job as a parent
is to ensure that by the time your child
is 4 years old that they are maximally
desirable to other children and two
adults because what happens is that
after the age of four
you aren't the primary agent of
socialization if the social world
becomes the primary agent of
socialization and if your child is the
sort of child that's invited to play by
other children because your child is
capable of four strolling gratification
and taking turns and playing someone
else's game when when it's necessary and
abiding by the rules and not having a
temper tantrum when they lose and not
getting to you know high on their horse
when they win then many children will
invite them no III know we have we have
our limited time and so I just wanted to
I was actually say any more question
because I really want to hear you talk
well oh I know I just want to let it all
take 15 seconds to wrap that up in this
well so look you get married when you
have your children and you're flawed and
your partner's flawed and hopefully
you're flawed in different ways and so
you put the two of you together and you
make one approximately normal person and
then hopefully and then your child has
to interact with that dyad that is a
reasonable representative of social
norms and if they discipline if your
child disappoints you with their
behavior the probability that they will
disappoint other people is very high and
so you have an ethical obligation to
ensure that your child is behaving in a
manner that makes them optimally
desirable to their playmates and also to
other adults because then people the
kids invite them to play and they get to
be socialized right they get they have
friends for God's sake is like what do
you want for your kids how about some
friends wouldn't that be nice and maybe
what you'd like is that they regulate
their behavior well enough so that when
you take them places restaurants to see
your
friends to see your relatives they
behave in a manner that sufficiently
civilized so their intrinsic charm wins
over the adults and everywhere they go
people are smiling and welcoming instead
of wishing with fake smiles that the
damn brat would leave along with their
foolish parents which is not a good
that's not a good environment to have
your child constantly exposed to no
friends because they're too selfish and
immature and irritated you're irritating
two adults so that they're barely
tolerated under the mask of false smiles
it's like you have an ethical obligation
to regulate your child's behavior so
that they're optimally acceptable
socially and that is not how people look
at children in the modern world they
think well you're raising their
self-esteem or you're enhancing their
creativity or you don't want to put
constraints on their behavior because
you're going to interfere with the
flowering of their intrinsic self and
you know it's all Rousseau in nonsense
and there's no evidence yeah such a
corrupt and he had these babies with
this poor scullery maid and left them
all in a actually a place where they
would just languish and die yeah right
five of them Rousseau yeah I know I know
yeah exactly oh man is intrinsically
good yeah but I just remember a few
weeks ago I was I really met you in and
somehow I got onto somebody's Twitter
feed whom I will not mention because oh
my god that anyway a difficult person
and she was attacking you and had a
selection from your book a way you had
called two-year-olds little monsters and
so suddenly all of these distraught
Twitter followers of this feminist were
saying occasionally there'd be a parent
who would take they kind of
two-year-olds kind of are monsters you
know and then there'd be a and they kind
of are and they had taken this out of
context and shown it like just something
to deplore it and it was so amusing Tim
this little hopefully they'll soon be
cursed with some two years I won't say
which one was two years old and had he
was a good boy but he had an insane
meltdown in a supermarket I was with my
mother
we both pretended we didn't know oh yeah
oh yeah we heard people say oh my god Oh
haven't watching a two-year-old have a
tantrum is it so it was very like I
didn't want to be a we had a boy who
used to be in like when my wife was
taking care of more kids than ours there
was a little boy who had learned to
throw a pretty decent tab yes and and he
would do that and it didn't work in our
house because we just leave him have his
tantrum and going into a different room
and then he'd kind of wake up out of it
there wouldn't be anybody around and so
that like if you put all that we're not
in dramatic display and you had zero
audience it's not you're not gonna
sustain it anyways he could actually
hold his breath until he turned blue so
you should try that you go home and see
if you can do that in front of the
mirror man like it's hard it's very very
dire
will you do it was impressive it was and
and you know two-year-olds are very
impressive they're there they have
unbelievable outbursts of rage and and
disinhibited emotion and your job is you
know they're they're driven by these
underlying motivational systems that are
unbelievably powerful and it's part of
what makes them delightful because when
they're happy they're insanely happy and
when they're playful they're incredibly
playful and so the positive end of them
is is way exaggerated compared to you
know a rather drab adult and and so it
makes two-year-olds extraordinarily
interesting but the same is true on the
negative emotion side they're completely
dysregulated and it's really hard on
them like to have a two-year-old who
isn't in control of their emotions means
that you have a child who's developing
central personality you know their their
ego for black of a better word is
constantly being swamped by these
powerful underlying emotional systems
you know what it's like if you are
enraged for any period of time or if
you're engulfed by grief like it's
exhausting it's it's it's demeaning and
it's exhausting and it's the same with a
little candidates like it's a real
defeat for the developing integrated
individual
to be subjugated by those catastrophic
ly powerful emergent emotions and part
of your job as a parent is to scaffold
the part of the child that can regulate
and inhibit those powerful underlying
systems so with my son for example when
he used to misbehave I would count and
say you're gonna go sit on the steps
he'd say oh no I'm not I would say oh
yes you are
and then usually I'd have to chase him
around because he wouldn't go sit on the
steps and so I'd put him on the steps
say you're gonna sit there until you've
got yourself under control
and so he'd say no I not say yes you are
and then he tried to get up and I just
told him say you're gonna sit there I'm
gonna hold you till you sit there no or
not it's like I could no wait a
two-year-old so I usually won those
battles and then he'd sit there I'd say
look kid this is the deal I'd say two
things like you won't have a bad day or
you won't have a good day you think
about that because if you don't have a
good day a bad day we could have a bad
days you sit here as soon as you can
controlling yourself and you ready to be
civilized then you can come back and we
can have a good day
so we'd sit there just just I was
unbelievable to watch just enveloped
with rage you know just trying to get
himself under control you know and so
I'd come back thirty seconds later and
I'd say you know what good got yourself
caught your act together you know yeah
so then I wait and usually it took him
two or three minutes and he'd calm down
and then he'd come back out and you'd
say I'm ready to have a good day and he
meant it you know and I could tell he
meant it too because whatever resentment
I was harboring towards him for his
misbehavior and you have to watch that
when you're an adult would vanish
because he'd come and he he was done he
was ready just you know to proceed on a
civilized basis it was really
interesting to watch that because it
took him every time he sat on the steps
it took him a shorter and shorter period
of time to attain mastery right until
you know it got to the point where he
could only have to sit for 15 seconds or
so when he would bring himself under
control and that was a victory like you
if you imagine the neurological systems
developed that are responsible for
personality integration
a victory for those systems because they
were attaining the ability to regulate
the lower order spontaneous emotions and
you know and and he turned into an
individual who's capable of a tremendous
level of self control and you know and
he had large team with yes absolutely
and well it turned out well for my
daughter too because she ended up being
very ill and he ended up being
extraordinarily level-headed and
reliable and thank God for that could
you could you come to my house and do
that for my little Maltipoo Izzy cuz I
got I can't she I can't I can't train
her she's like one night the next book
the dog
I would love how to train your dog
before tea yeah what is the one rule my
what's with petting the cat I wrote
about dogs for two pages to begin with
just to satisfy the dog it didn't
satisfy you can't satisfy them alright
well we can't thank you enough for
coming here I know the AEI audience is
just so delighted to have had the chance
to hear you well I'm really happy good
to chance to talk my weights of talk
I've only met you like once we met in DC
but I just see you passed electron yes
oh you swiped
oh yeah well there was that we're not
going into that
[Applause]